<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://sarahsmithtripp.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://sarahsmithtripp.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-12-21T16:48:37+00:00</updated><id>https://sarahsmithtripp.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Sarah Smith-Tripp</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Becoming a Foreign Pilot</title><link href="https://sarahsmithtripp.github.io/blog/2023/BecomeADronePilot/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Becoming a Foreign Pilot"/><published>2023-07-11T20:16:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-11T20:16:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sarahsmithtripp.github.io/blog/2023/BecomeADronePilot</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sarahsmithtripp.github.io/blog/2023/BecomeADronePilot/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="my-drone-journey-how-i-became-a-foreign-pilot">My drone journey; how I became a foreign pilot</h1> <p>We are going to take a brief break from talking about the research sites we are visiting on our journey to discuss some of the logistics that come with drone research.ui Introducing my co-writer Leanna, another fellow PhD student that just completed some drone field work on Vancouver Island. &lt;/div&gt;</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/Leanna_Drone-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/Leanna_Drone-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/Leanna_Drone-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/Leanna_Drone.jpg" width="auto" height="auto"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Leanna Stackhouse out in the field flying our dearest drone - Loretta! </div> <p>She also just had her first Phd paper published (congrats!). Check out her work here: Stackhouse, L., Coops, N.C., White, J.C., Davis, D.J, (2023) Characterizing riparian vegetation and classifying riparian extent using airborne laser scanning data.~Ecological Indicators~. 152. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecolind.2023.110366</p> <p>We are both UBC graduate students from the United States. I (Sarah) have flown drones since 2020 for both my Master’s and PhD research. Leanna started working with drones in 2023. We both had fairly similar yet ultimately different experiences applying for our SFOC’s as drone legislation is constantly changing. This post discusses the most recent application process for a foreignors to be able to fly drones in Canada. Note: we are not a legal advisors, and only describe the process to make it easier for other graduate students to fly drones for their own data collection processes.</p> <p>Foreign pilots must apply for a Special Flight Operations Certificate (SFOC) issued by Transport Canada. With this certificate, Leanna and I can fly in unregulated (class G) airspace until the end of the year. Any foreign pilot must have an SFOC to fly a drone in Canada (for any purpose too!). This post does discuss the process of applying for advanced operations as our forest research sites are generally very remote.</p> <p>Before applying for an SFOC there are several steps you must take prior:</p> <ol> <li>A drone pilot certificate. If you are flying in unregulated airspace you need to pass the <strong>basic operations</strong> drone exam and include this is in your application.</li> <li>A drone registered with Transport Canada. Our drones are registered with our supervisor and we include their registration number and VIN in our applications. A foreign pilot cannot register their own drones. In addition to the registration you must provide: <ul> <li>Manufacturer details of the drone system</li> <li>A history of the maintenance on the system</li> </ul> </li> <li>Contact information 4 The type of drone operation and an example of your pre-flight safety plan</li> <li>Description of the drone operation including: <ul> <li>Purpose</li> <li>Dates</li> </ul> </li> <li>A safety plan for the proposed operation. If you are interested in copy of my safety plan shoot me an email (ssmithtr@wellesley.edu) <ul> <li>The safety plan must include a contingency plan for the operation including emergency operations <ul> <li>Describe all equipment and personel to respond to emergencies (This is why I always carry kitty litter!)</li> <li>Describe all communication protocols</li> </ul> </li> </ul> </li> <li>An operation plan. Our safety and operation plans are combined on a google form. Our safety and operation plans are generally combined. These safety plans must include: <ul> <li>A description of operation including the order of events and objectives</li> <li>A site-survey with a clear depiction of the area, with boundaries expected altitudes, and hazards.</li> <li>An adequate risk assessment.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Names, certificates, licenses, permits and qualifications of the crew members. This includes both the pilot and visual observers.</li> </ol> <p>This all sounds like a lot - but once you get these all compiled you can fill out the necessary documentation. These documents include the following forms:</p> <ol> <li>Application form</li> <li>An SOFC Compliance Matrix that details the locations where you can find all of the different components listed above (I generally put the page numbers in one big combined document)</li> <li>We also recommend including a cover letter. I encourage the TC Canada staff to call me if they have any problems. It is a great idea because I have been called twice and was able to quickly fix my error on the phone!</li> </ol> <p>Here is a great visualization of this whole process. &lt;/div&gt;</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/Drone_flow-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/Drone_flow-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/Drone_flow-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/Drone_flow.jpg" width="auto" height="auto"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Workflow of the process to apply for a special flight operations certificate. </div> <p>We hope this blog-post is a helpful resource for those that are interested in become foriegn pilots - we love our drones because they give us so much great data!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="scantiques"/><category term="drone,"/><category term="Remotely"/><category term="Piloted"/><category term="Aircraft,"/><category term="scantiques"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It's rare for me to fly a proper experiment!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Real Time Kinematic Processing</title><link href="https://sarahsmithtripp.github.io/blog/2023/RealTimeKinematicRTK/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Real Time Kinematic Processing"/><published>2023-07-10T10:43:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-10T10:43:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sarahsmithtripp.github.io/blog/2023/RealTimeKinematicRTK</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sarahsmithtripp.github.io/blog/2023/RealTimeKinematicRTK/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="lets-talk-about-satellites">Let’s talk about satellites!</h1> <p>We have spent the last couple of days blasting across the prairies. To navigate from to place we have been heavily on a technology important for navigation of both people and drones. This post is dedicated to the unseed hero of drone-based remote sensing - the satellite. Specifically, satellites that are members of the elite suite of satellites referred to as our <strong>Global Naviation Satellite System</strong> (GNSS). These satellites constantly transmit data that when used in combination with at least four other positioning satellites can give a precise location. The world of positioning is very exciting so let’s dive in!</p> <p>The first thing to know is that the moniker “GPS” or Global Positioning System is misleading. There five distinct GNSS systems available for positioning. These systems are:</p> <ol> <li>GPS; deployed in 1978 and publicly available since 1994</li> <li>Quasi-Zenith Satellite System (QZSS); publicly available since 2018 but only covers Eastern Asia</li> <li>BEIDOU; a Chinese satellite system that is now fully available (2020) with global coverage</li> <li>GALILEO; a European Union satellite system available since 2016</li> <li>GLONASS; Russian GNSS system with global coverage since 2011</li> </ol> <p>For our phones to give us our 3D location, they use a technique called <strong>trilateration</strong>.Trilateration is frequently confused with triangulation. Both of these processes uses overlap, but trilateration uses overlap of ranges, or distances between a satellite and a reciever, to get either a 2D or 3D location. Triangulation uses overlap of angles on lines. You can see an outline of trilateration below. Any GPS receiver uses this process, your phone, your car, even airplanes! Yet, our phones gives us accuracies in the meter (5 + meter) or multimeter (10 + meters) accuracy when our research interested in sub-meter accuracy. For example, what is the precise position of a tree impacted by root rot (tune into for Madi’s guest blog post on this soon!). These accuracy levels are determined by satellite coverage, atmospheric interference, and direct control from the US government. To increase accuracy level of our data we use a process called <strong>real time kinematic</strong> or RTK.</p> <p>&lt;/div&gt;</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/Satelite_Outline-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/Satelite_Outline-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/Satelite_Outline-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/Satelite_Outline.png" width="auto" height="auto"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Method of trilateration to get a satellite fix. </div> <h2 id="real-time-kinematic-positioning">Real Time Kinematic Positioning</h2> <p>In a prior blog post I discussed some of the problems of drone work - one of the biggest being satellite connection for both the drone and a GNSS base-station. We use RTK processing where the drone and GNSS base-station work in tandem to give real-time centimeter accuracy data. Our M300 drone uses all but the QZSS GNSS systems to collect data accurate to the centimeter level. With RTK, the drone, which is also called a rover, links to an unmoving GNSS base-station that records the same satellite information at the same time. RTK uses the known distance between the stationary base station and the drone to correct for satellite associated errors resulting from issues with the satellite location, atmospheric interference, and reflection of signal that might confuse the GNSS receiver. In RTK systems, such corrections are done in real-time, but these corrections can also be done after data collection using a process called <strong>Post-Processing Kinematic</strong> (PPK). We don’t use PPK processing that often in our research, but I should mention the main advantage of PPK over RTK is that if the drone and base station lose connection, you can still get accurate locations with later processing. However, RTK is what allows our drone to keep exact positioning, land at exactly the same spot, and make sure that it covers all of the flight plan.</p> <p>The schematic below describes the overall process. Satellites send out signals that define the exact time that the signal is sent out - this is called the <strong>code phase</strong>. Our GPS receivers then align their own clocks to the time of the satellite to get time that it took the signal be received. The signal travels at the speed of light, which is a constant, so we can use the time multiplied by the speed to get the distance. However, errors introduced while sending the signal and the receiving the signal can cause minute errors. These minute errors, multiplied by the speed of light cause large errors in positioning. Luckily, we can also use the frequency that comes alongside the <strong>code phase</strong>, the <strong>carrier phase</strong>, which operates at a much higher frequency with much lower error margins which better parse errors in our positioning. Code phase is easily disentangled from different satellites, carrier phase is less so. In an RTK system the base station and the rover lock onto the same satellites with their code-phases and use these positions to pinpoint a more exact location from the carrier phases. All of that seems really complex! To simplify let’s look at the process as a whole:</p> <h2 id="the-rtk-process">The RTK process:</h2> <ol> <li>The GNSS base station and a rover (i.e. the drone) lock onto the same satellites</li> <li>Using the satellites, the base station and the rover approximate their positions</li> <li>With the known distance between the base station and the information sent by the same satellites the unmoving base station updates and corrects the rovers location in real-time. *Note: in RTK processing this position of the rover is relative to the base station. We have to link the base station to a known geographic point for our final accuracy to be as correct as possible.</li> </ol> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/RTK_process-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/RTK_process-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/RTK_process-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/RTK_process.png" width="auto" height="auto"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> An overview of the RTK and PPK systems. The different signals sent by the satellite are shown by the lines. </div> <p>I hope that this post has started to unravel the complex world of GNSS positioning. It is really crazy how much we rely on this complex technology!</p> <h2 id="key-science-terms">Key Science Terms</h2> <ul> <li><strong>Trilateration</strong>: Using a combination of distances from an object (or ranges) to get the 2D or 3D ‘fix’ or precise location. For GNSS recievers, they need to receive transmission from 4 unique satellites.</li> <li><strong>rover</strong>: A moving GNSS receiver that is part of a two part GPS receiving system.</li> <li><strong>Base station</strong>: A GNSS receiver that does not move during data collection and generally has a precise known location on earth.</li> <li><strong>Real-Time Kinematic</strong> : A system of satellite receivers (a GNSS base station and a rover) that work in tandem to adjust errors in satellite signals to get exact final positions. RTK will make these corrections in real-time.</li> <li><strong>Post-Processing Kinematic</strong> : A similiar combination of a GNSS base station and a rover that collect data from satellites simultanously, but are not actively transmitting data to eachother. The base station has a known location that is used to adjust errors in the rover after data collection.</li> <li><strong>code phase</strong>: The unique time signal sent out by a satellite and aligned by a GPS reciever to give the distance between the satellite and the receiver.</li> <li><strong>carrier phase</strong>: A higher frequency signal sent out by a satellite that helps pinpoint location more precisely.</li> </ul> <h2 id="resources">Resources</h2> <p>If your are curious to learn more here are some the resources I consulted to write this blog: *<a href="https://letstalkscience.ca/educational-resources/backgrounders/math-behind-gps"> The math behind GPS </a>. *<a href="https://www.jouav.com/blog/rtk-drone.html"> Jouav: how an RTK drone works </a>. *<a href="https://www.hammermissions.com/post/how-to-achieve-highly-accurate-flights-with-the-dji-m300-rtk"> Hammer missions processing with an RTK drone </a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="scantiques"/><category term="drone,"/><category term="satellite,"/><category term="gps,"/><category term="surveying"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Highly Accurate Positions for our Trees <3]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Droughting experiments in New Brunswick</title><link href="https://sarahsmithtripp.github.io/blog/2023/DroughtingBlackbrook/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Droughting experiments in New Brunswick"/><published>2023-07-05T17:43:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-05T17:43:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sarahsmithtripp.github.io/blog/2023/DroughtingBlackbrook</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sarahsmithtripp.github.io/blog/2023/DroughtingBlackbrook/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="blackbrook-research-forest-drought-and-thinning">Blackbrook Research Forest Drought and Thinning</h1> <p>&lt;/div&gt;</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blackbrook_team-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blackbrook_team-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blackbrook_team-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/blackbrook_team.jpg" width="auto" height="auto"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> A Silva21 team at the Blackbrook research site! From left: Shane Furze, Katie Tripp, Madi Brown, Chloe Larstone Hunt, Sarah Smith-Tripp, Evan Muise </div> <p>As a remote-sensing data-scientists most of my data is observed from the earth surface. As an observer, I do not directly manipulate my study sites. Thus, it was exciting to go out to an experiment that built and implemented treatments to test the relationship between <strong>independent</strong> and <strong>dependent</strong> variables. An independent variable is a variable that is manipulated to test if the dependent variable will change as a response. In the drought experiment we visited, which is the MSc Chloe Larstone Hunt at University of New Brunswick, there are two independent variables (1) level of thinning between trees and (2) level of drought. Each of these independent variables have <strong>strata</strong> or levels: (1a) high thinning and (1000 stems per hectare) (1b) intermediate thinning (1500 stems per hectare) and (1c) low thinning (2000-3000 stems per hectare). The second independent variable is drought level. These are: (2a) no drought (2b) 25% drought and (2c) 50% drought. This gives a total of nine combinations. In science, you need <strong>replication</strong> so there are 18 plots (2 replications) in this exciting drought experiment.</p> <p>I have always been interested in this project because it is a tree-sized version of the famous and wide-spread drought network (DroughtNet) which is a global network of experiments with standard protocols that allow us to better stand the impact of drought in many different environments. You can learn more at their webset(<a href="https://droughtnet.weebly.com/"> DroughtNet </a>). While this <a href="https://www.silva21.com/projects/rainfall-exclusion-experiment%3A-the-effect-of-thinning?lang=en"> Silva21 </a> is not part of DroughtNet - it is one of the first experiments to use a similiar structure to look at things larger than low-lying vegetation - trees!</p> <p>We got to the site early because we had a long drive to Quebec. The site is located deep in JD Irving’s private landbase. Along the 40 minute drive we passed two different JD Irving sawmills. The scale of Irving’s forest operation is something to behold, and something that can be hard to understand if you are not there to experience it yourself.</p> <p>The site itself is small, and I knew it would take less than 30 minutes to fly. I was optimistic about satellite connection because it was flat and open - a dream for accurate GPS. We took the opportunity to explore the different experimental strata. We clambered over a massive network of PVC pipes and timber to explore the nine types plots. In plots that are droughted, a plastic tarp lies at diameter at breast height or <strong>DBH</strong> and directs water away from the ground (where the tree roots are) to a PVC pipe network that deposits the water downslope from the site itself. In the 25% drought, 25% of the plot area is covered plastic tarping, and the same but greater in the 50% plots. In half the sites, some of the trees have been removed - theoretically water stress from competition.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blackbrook_exp-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blackbrook_exp-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blackbrook_exp-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/blackbrook_exp.jpg" width="auto" height="auto"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The network of PVC and timber that makes up the droughting experiment. </div> <p>Chloe and her lab mate Katie Tripp (the first Tripp I am not related to I have ever met!) are measuring the seasonal growth metrics and confirming the soil water differences among plots. They measure seasonal growth using <strong>dendrometer bands</strong> which monitor the change in <strong>DBH</strong> for the trees. Trees will constrict (minorly) when water stressed - so it is great way to see how trees may adjust to droughting.</p> <h2 id="undroughting-experiments-in-new-brunswick">Undroughting Experiments in New Brunswick</h2> <p>I have just spent the first part of this blog post discussing an droughting experiment, but now I want to switch gears to discuss an important “undroughting” experiment we have been conducting throughout New Brunswick. You can see a sample of the trial below:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/Picaroons_beers-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/Picaroons_beers-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/Picaroons_beers-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/Picaroons_beers.jpg" width="auto" height="auto"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> A beer flight at Picaroons in Fredricton! </div> <p>You guessed it - the craft beer scene. While New Brunswick may not be known for its breweries, we three Vancouverites (which is known for its craft breweries), want to change that. The beers I had in New Brunswick are some of the best beers I have had in in North America. Here is a ranking of the beers from each field member (<strong>don’t worry we shared!</strong>)</p> <h2 id="sarahs-top-beers">Sarah’s Top Beers</h2> <ol> <li>Epoutnique Hazy IPA - Brasseurs Du Petit-Sault <ul> <li><strong>remarks</strong> - “This beer is the best hazy IPA I have ever had, the perfect combination of not too citrusy and not too sour. It just works.”</li> </ul> </li> <li>Simeon Jones Amber Ale - Picaroons Brewing</li> <li>“Craft” - Novum Boreas</li> <li>Serie Epic Strawberry Rhubarb Sessional Lager - Brasseurs Du Petit-Sault</li> <li>Strawberry Lime Margarita Sour - York County Cider</li> <li>506 Golden Ale - Picaroons Brewing</li> <li>Swallowtail Light - Picaroons Brewing</li> <li>Irish Red -Picaroons Brewing</li> </ol> <h2 id="madis-top-beers">Madi’s Top Beers</h2> <ol> <li>Epoutnique Hazy IPA - Brasseurs Du Petit-Sault <ul> <li><strong>remarks</strong> - “Wow what a refreshing summer beer!”</li> </ul> </li> <li>Souer Catherine</li> <li>“Craft” - Nuvum Boreas</li> <li>Melon Head - Picaroons</li> <li>Snap Dickie - Brasseurs Du Petit-Sault</li> </ol> <h2 id="evan-buds-top-beers">Evan (Bud’s) Top Beers</h2> <ol> <li>Pop Rouge - Brasseurs Du Petit-Sault</li> <li>Epoutnique Hazy IPA - Brasseurs Du Petit-Sault</li> <li>Souer Catherine Old School IPA - Brasseurs Du Petit-Sault</li> <li>Melon Head - Picaroons</li> <li>Summer Sour Ale - Brasseurs Du Petit-Sault</li> <li>Strawberry Lime Margarita Cide - York County Cider</li> </ol> <p>So where are we know? Deep in Northern Ontario - stay tuned for a post on how I, an international student became a Remotely Piloted Aircraft (RPA) pilot in Canada!</p> <h2 id="key-science-terms">Key Science Terms</h2> <ul> <li><strong>Independent Variable</strong>: The variable that is changed to understand an impact or effect. In typical experiments (like the Blackbrook drought study) this is the variable that is changed by the researcher (thinning and drought).</li> <li><strong>Dependent Variable</strong>: The variable that is measured to test the response. This is not changed by the researcher but is measured (the dendrometer measurements)</li> <li><strong>Strata</strong> : Levels of an experiment treatment. In the blackbook site this goes from no drought, 25 % drought and 50 % drought (three strata)</li> <li><strong>replication</strong> : Sets or repeats in an experiment that have the same independent variable manipulations. There are two of the same plot types in the Blackbrook research experiment.</li> <li><strong>Diameter at Breast Height (DBH)</strong> : A famous measure for tree scientists. This is a critical metric for modeling tree volume, growth, and stand development. It’s so important that if you ask any forest scientist what height on their body is DBH they can immediately tell you because they need to know every time they walk up to a tree.</li> <li><strong>Dendrometer Bands</strong>: Metal bands installed on trees (generally at DBH) that give precise growth measurments. Measures made before and after the growing season show annual growth rates. Blackbrook also has electronic dendrometer bands installed that measure changes every 15 seconds. This gives a constant measure of the trees. Droughts generally decrease the daily changes in tree diameters, so we can better see strees.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="scantiques"/><category term="drone,"/><category term="field-work,"/><category term="scantiques"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It's rare for me to fly a proper experiment!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The trials of drone field work</title><link href="https://sarahsmithtripp.github.io/blog/2023/dronefieldwork/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The trials of drone field work"/><published>2023-07-04T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-04T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sarahsmithtripp.github.io/blog/2023/dronefieldwork</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sarahsmithtripp.github.io/blog/2023/dronefieldwork/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/Trees_inway-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/Trees_inway-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/Trees_inway-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/Trees_inway.jpg" width="auto" height="auto"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h1 id="the-trials-of-drone-field-work">The Trials of Drone Field Work</h1> <p>Last post I introduced our cross-country road trip and some of the awesome field work we are doing. We spent yesterday flying a site in Northern New Brunswick. We learned this morning that these sites cross New Brunswick. I find it exciting to contribute to such a large research project, but am still learning site details. In lieu of science, this post describes a typical day of drone field work. Throughout this post I wil point out places were things can <strong>AND</strong> will (or rather did) go wrong. Let’s dive in!</p> <h2 id="a-day-of-drone-field-work">A day of Drone Field Work:</h2> <h3 id="the-night-before">The Night Before</h3> <p>The night before fieldwork starts with an equipment list. On the scantiques road show we are driving a Ford Ranger which is stacked to the top with cases for our sensitive instruments and safety equipment. We even have a case with our personal gear strapped on top! So what is packed into this truck?</p> <ul> <li>DJI M300 drone and controller</li> <li>1-2 battery cases storing batteries, controller, and GPS base-station</li> <li>1-2 DJI mini-drones</li> <li>A large-long case storing the GPS base-station</li> <li>A Trimble GPS base-staton (yes we need two)</li> <li>Sensors including: <ul> <li>DJI Zenmuse L1 (Lidar)</li> <li>DJI P1 (a very fancy camera)</li> <li>A multiband camera (this is in-lie of the <strong>hyperspectral</strong> camera I described yesterday)</li> </ul> </li> <li>field laptop</li> <li>Starlink internet</li> <li>generator (to re-charge drones throughout the day)</li> <li>gas can (to fill the generator)</li> <li>rangefinder</li> <li>hardhats</li> <li>cruising safety vests</li> <li>Radios (and chargers)</li> <li>Cooler</li> <li>Pop-up tent for rain and sun</li> <li>Camping chairs for the crew on long field days</li> <li>All of our personal gear for 3 weeks away</li> </ul> <p>To protect this mountain of gear - we bring all of it into our hotel rooms. In the hotel room, we dedicate all outlets for drone gear charging creating a constant whirr of charging electronics. Before bed, the pilot in the command plans the next day’s flight on drones remote controller by down loading a shapefile for the site and looking at satellite imagery.</p> <h3 id="the-morning-of">The Morning Of</h3> <p>Many of the field sites we visit are 1-2 hours from the forest sites where we are working. We often wake up early, visit the local Tim Hortons, and head out to the field. Here is where we ran into issue (1) of the day - the need for an oil change. On Sunday, when we turned the truck key, we got a flashing light for <strong>OIL CHANGE REQUIRED</strong>, but Monday was a federal holiday. Open garages were hard to find. Canadian Tire seemed like it might be open, so we booked an appointment for 9 am yesterday. While it first seemed as though the Canadian Tire was also closed, they eventually agreed to change the oil. It took two hours, and my field team can provide you with a full review of Canadian Tire patio furniture - but we made it on the road before the afternoon.</p> <h3 id="at-the-site">At the site</h3> <p>We made it to our first of two sites just before noon. My field crew operates much like a race car pit-crew. The race car is the drone. To run, a drone needs a pilot with a flight plan (me - Sarah), connection to satellites and the base-station, a fresh set of batteries, and the sensor installed. Generally, the pilot runs all things data heavy. I get to the site and verify the site plan. The crew sets up the GPS base-station, takes the drone out of the case and installs new batteries. Last, I install the sensor, turn on the drone, and pray to the heavens. No, literally I look to the sky in hope and anguish. Any number of errors can come up at this point, the most frequent for closed forests of Canada is poor satellite connection. The drone will not fly with less than 10 satellites and an active connection with the GPS base station getting signal from those same satellites. Luckily at the first site the odds were in our favor 30+ satellites quickly connected. We were ready to fly!</p> <h3 id="mid-flight">Mid-flight</h3> <p>Once the drone takes off I monitor it as it goes to its flight start point. During the flight the drone executes the flight plan with little direction from the pilot. My role as the pilot is to make sure the drone has enough battery power, is not in danger from obstacles or birds (it happens), and is collecting the correct data. While in flight, I keep line of sight and connection by climbing on top of the field truck or running down the road. On the controller, I check to make sure that the drone is not close to trees. Every 20-30 minutes the drone has to land for a battery change. Here, the pit-crew returns to rapidly replace the battery so we can get the drone back up in the air. They take care of managing the number of batteries we have left, when we run low on batteries the pit crew will start the generator to make sure that we don’t run out.</p> <h3 id="end-of-flight">End of flight</h3> <p>After the drone finishes the flight path it automatically returns home. I collect the data from the sensor and we take down the small drone-focused camp that surrounds the truck. We pile it all into the truck and continue onto the next site. At the end of the day, I back up the data to a computer and a harddrive and make sure that all of the data is there.</p> <h3 id="summmary">Summmary</h3> <p>This is what happens when all goes as planned. This is exactly what happened for the first site - not the case for the second site. Here, what should have been a 1.5-hour flight turned into a 5-hour adventure. The first thing to go wrong was access to the site. Anyone who has walked a trail in the early spring knows just how many trees can fall in the winter. While humans have the ability to clamber over trees and branches, clearing the path for a truck requires saws, tools, and a couple hours. When trying to get to the second site we quickly found that no-one had been there in a while - countless trees blocked what we thought would be perfect site access.</p> <p>Luckily, there was a road on the other side of a small stream from the site. We thought we could fly from there. We drove over, set up, and turned on the drone. This time, the satellites were not in our favor. There was not enough signal for the drone to fly. We were deep in a forested river valley, so when the drone system told us to fix the error by ‘moving to a more open area or power-cycling the drone,’ our only option was to power cycle and wait. Which we did. Once. Twice. Three times. A bathroom break and a soda-water later, just one more time. And again. After an hour had passed, we had to try something new. I walked down the road to try and find another spot - higher ground, fewer trees, anything. I found a site that was about the same quality as where we were and radioed the team to pack up the truck - we were moving. We moved and set up for another attempt. We set up and turned on the drone again - no luck. Another power cycle. Some contemplation on what to do when I look down and see - we had satellite! Moving quickly, I pulled up the flight plan, did my pre-flight check, and launched the drone. We were off!</p> <p>We were flying! For a while… The first problem was the site was long. To keep line-of-sight on the drone, I had to fast-walk alongside the flight route, which paralleled the road. I bid adieu to the pit-crew in pursuit of the drone. All was well until the first battery switch. After landing and hot-swapping the batteries, the drone flew to the pause-point in the flight plan and immediately lost satellite connection. To maintain accurate data collection, the drone and the GPS station need constant satellite connection - the two work in tandem to collect data at sub-centimeter level precision and accuracy. After trying to reconnect, I was forced to land and see if it might connect again. After 15 minutes of ground time, the drone remarkably connected again. Take off part 2! We successfully flew another 50% of the 1.5-hour flight before we lost satellite connection. RATS! Another landing, more downtime, and another remarkable reconnection! Take off part 3! At this point, the clock read 4:45, and thunderclouds loomed in the distance. Time was of the essence. The flight neared completion (97%) - almost there! And lo, another lost satellite connection. Disaster! But with thunder threatening, I finished the flight, praying that the redundancy I built in the flight plans (overlap and buffer areas) will salvage the overall accuracy of the lidar final product.</p> <p>So there we have it - one day, one perfect drone flight execution, and a second drone flight that felt like it would never end. Tune in tomorrow for an update on our last field site in New Brunswick - a drought exclusion collaboration with University of New Brunswick and JD Irving!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="scantiques"/><category term="drone,"/><category term="field-work,"/><category term="scantiques"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Sometimes drone field work feels like the future, but the future is NOT perfect]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Scantiques Roadshow</title><link href="https://sarahsmithtripp.github.io/blog/2023/ScantiquesDay1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scantiques Roadshow"/><published>2023-07-03T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-03T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://sarahsmithtripp.github.io/blog/2023/ScantiquesDay1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sarahsmithtripp.github.io/blog/2023/ScantiquesDay1/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="bienvenue-sur-le-grand-voyage--welcome-to-the-big-trip">Bienvenue Sur le Grand Voyage / Welcome to the Big Trip!</h1> <p>Join me on my coast-to-coast journey as part of the Silva21 (my PhD project’s parent grant) ‘Scan-tiques’ road tour. So-called ‘Scan-Tiques’ as we are conducting 3D laser scans using <strong>Lidar</strong> in many different forests along our way home to Vancouver. These 3D scans show the tree structure and the topography. You can see an example of this in GIF below:</p> <iframe src="https://giphy.com/embed/r4II1ThDbD4ZgLEq3E" width="480" height="270" frameborder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowfullscreen=""></iframe> <p><a href="https://giphy.com/gifs/r4II1ThDbD4ZgLEq3E">Scantiques in Action!</a></p> <p>There is a huge advantage of Lidar data for forest structure. In fact, when I queried Web of Science we can see its application to science has increased radidly over the last ten years. Just look at how the number of publications has changed!</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/knowledge_citations-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/knowledge_citations-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/knowledge_citations-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/knowledge_citations.jpg" width="auto" height="auto"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The number of publications looking at Lidar and forest structure in the last 20 years. Search terms are: "Lidar OR Laser Scanning OR ALS or Drone Lidar AND Forest AND Structure OR Vegetation OR composition" </div> <p>Our journey started in Nova Scotia at Oak Island Conference Center after the Silva21 Annual General Meeting. We will finish in two weeks back home in Vancouver, BC. Here is a list of the sites we will visit on our way back home.</p> <h4 id="sites">Sites</h4> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>1. Acadia Research Forest (two experiments)
2. A spruce trial in northern New Brunswick (perfect time to practice french!)
3. Drought Exclusion in New Brunswick
4. Commercial Thinning in Nipigon, Ontario 
5. Spruce-Pine planting in interio British Columbia
</code></pre></div></div> <h2 id="where-are-we-now">Where are we now?</h2> <p>I am writing this blog post four days into our trip with two very full days of flying under our belt. We spent Canada Day (Saturday) in Acadia Research Forest flying two different sites: (1) a flight in a cutblock which will be planted with 10 different tree species of all different geographic origins (a project called TransX) and (2) a site of older red-spruce of mixed genetic origins. In this post, I am going to highlight the first site, TransX, and the new technology we helped deploy at the second site. In these blogs, I am going to keep a list important scientific topics. Check out the list at the base of this blog for detailed definitions.</p> <h2 id="transx">TransX</h2> <p>TransX is a <strong>common garden</strong> experiment for common East Coast tree species. A common garden experiment places plants with parents of different geographic origins in the same common growing experiment. In TransX – a Sugar Maple (Acer Saccarum) whose parent trees are from Virginia might be planted right next to a Sugar Maple whose parent trees are from southern New Brunswick. One goal of TransX is to test the hypothesis if a tree from warmer climates will grow better in warmer conditions by planting trees from a colder climate in the same growing conditions and comparing the two.</p> <h2 id="new-hyperspectral-technology">New Hyperspectral Technology</h2> <p>At our second site we met up with Olivier Van Lier and Funda Ogut from Natural Resources Canada. This project recently acquired a novel <strong>hyperspectral</strong> drone made by headwall <a href="https://velodynelidar.com/automated-with-velodyne/headwall/"> headwall-hyperspectral </a>. What does hyperspectral mean? Great question! Surfaces – any type of surface – reflects electromagnetic waves that wavelength (or the length of wave) across a range referred to as the <strong>‘electromagnetic spectrum’</strong> or <strong>EMS</strong> for short. We see in the visible part of the EMS. Hyperspectral sees across the EMS and captures more unique colors than our eyes. This type of technology is extremely useful for seeing small differences in tree health. Here is a link to a paper that talks more: <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s40725-019-00096-1"> Paper-Link </a> We flew Lidar of the site and then spent some time trying to get the second drone up and running – but the calibration for hyperspectral imaging is INTENSE! While we did not stay around to see the hyperspectral drone (field work and weather called us away) – I did get the opportunity to fly my heaviest drone yet (a whole 6 pounds!). See a picture of the two drones below.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/double_drone-480.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/double_drone-800.webp"/> <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/double_drone-1400.webp"/> <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/double_drone.jpg" width="auto" height="auto"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The new Headwall drone with hyperspectral sensor (left) and the DJI Zenmuse (right) both mounted on DJI M300 drones. </div> <h2 id="key-science-terms">Key Science Terms</h2> <ul> <li>Lidar - Light detection and ranging: a method that emits a light-pulse from a sensor (ours is on a drone) and measures the time it takes for this sensor to return. Horizontal distance = time * speed of the light, and when done many times this gives 3D structures </li> <li>Common garden experiment: Plants with parents from geographic origins planted in the same common growing environment </li> <li>Electromagnetic spectrum (EMS): describe the different types of electromagnetic waves that exist. Ranges from radio waves to gamma waves and covers the visible range (what we see!) </li> <li>Hyperspectral imaging: captures all reflectance of an object in the EMS </li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="scantiques"/><category term="drones,"/><category term="common-garden,"/><category term="hyperspectral"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Scantiques Roadshow in Acadia Research Forest]]></summary></entry></feed>